- [Instructor] Hi and
welcome back to the course.
In this video and the next,
we're going to go over
how easy it is
to add more to our API
and make it more powerful.
We're going to do that by
adding the concept of stores,
in this video.
Let's go over to our models folder,
because we're going to start
by creating a new model
as opposed to a new resource.
That is because the resource
normally has to use the model
to extract data from the database,
the model kind of stands on itself.
Let's right click the models folder
and create
a store
.py file
and what we're gonna put in the store.py
is a copy of the item model,
so I'm just gonna select
everything there, copy it
and paste it in the store.py.
Now, of course we're gonna
change a few things here.
We're gonna call this StoreModel,
the table name is going to be stores,
it's not gonna have a price column,
it's just gonna have an id and a name.
The JSON method is going
to be slightly different
and that is going to be,
instead of name and price
it's going to be name and items
and here, we're going to put
self.items
and we're gonna get into exactly
how we get those items in a moment.
Okay?
The find_by_name is going
to be exactly the same,
we're going to be able to
retrieve a store by its name
and then we're gonna be
able to save to the database
and delete it from the database as well.
So, nothing there is going to change.
Now I have to make sure
that we have this self.items
thing.
Let's go to the item model, first,
and we're going to add something there.
What we're going to add
here is a new column
on the item.
This column is going to be store_id
and this is going to be an integer
because it has to match
exactly the store's id type
and it's also gonna have something else,
which is db.foreignkey
and the foreign key
is going to be stores,
which is the table name of the store,
.id, which is the column name.
Okay, so, what does this mean?
What is a foreign key
and why are we putting a store id here?
Well, let me show you
a small diagram, here.
Imagine that we have, well, we do have,
these two models: the
item and the store model.
If we create, say, three items
and they all have the same
store id, which is two,
and then we have a store
that has the id two
we can link them
in our minds
by saying that these three
items belong inside this store
or they are somehow
linked and that is because
we have the item, we have the store id
and therefore we can
then go to the database
and find the store that has this id.
Similarly, if we have the store,
we can go to the items table and find out
which items have the same store id
as this store's id.
So, we have the store model,
we can find all the
items that belong to it
and if we have an item
we can find out the store
that it belongs to.
So, they are somehow linked and this link
is caused or created by the foreign key.
The id in the store is a primary key
and the store id in the
item is a foreign key
because it has values
identical to the id values
of another table.
In this scenario, here,
where we have three items
with store id two and a store with id two,
we would not be able to delete this store.
The relational database engine,
such as SQL Lite or Postgres or My SQL
would not let you delete this store
because there are foreign key references.
So, you'd first have to delete these items
or move them somewhere
else, change the store id
before you can delete this store.
So, it allows us some degree
of control or security
and in knowing that these two are linked
and it's not just
in our heads
and so by using a foreign key
that gives us that security
that we can't delete things, for example.
Okay?
So, this is why we're adding
this store id to the model
because then we're going to be able to say
what store do we belong
to and we're gonna be able
to find the store.
But there would be a
way to do that with SQL,
with a join and we're going
to look at what a join is
in a future video
but we don't have to use joins
because SQLAlchemy does that for us.
All that we have to do is, now,
say store
is
db.relationship
storemodel and voila.
If you ever used joins in SQL in the past,
you'll be pleased to
know that you no longer
have to do that.
What this does now is that it sees
that we have a store id
and therefore we can find
a store in the database
that matches this store id.
So, now, every item model
has a property store
that is the store which
matches this store id
in its id.
Hopefully, all of that makes sense
but also we can do a back reference.
A back reference does the opposite.
It allows a store to see which items
are in the items database,
or in the items table,
with the store id equal to its own id.
The way we do that is
items equal db.relationship
itemmodel.
How easy is that?
Okay, so what that is doing it it's saying
we have a relationship with itemmodel
and then SQLAlchemy says, okay,
there's a relationship there
what's the relationship?
And then it goes into the item
and it finds that there's a store id here
and then it goes, ah-ha,
there's a store id in the item
which means
that one item is related to a store.
Therefore there could
be more than one item
related to the same store.
There could be two items
related to the store,
like in this example or three
items related to the store.
So it knows
that the store and the item,
this variable here, is a single store,
i.e.: there's only one store
that and item is related to
but the items variable in the store
can be many items, so, therefore,
if we go to the store this variable here
is a list of item models
because it knows that it is a
many-to-one relationship.
There could be many items
with the same store id.
So, hopefully all that makes sense
and now we can go back
here into self.items
and we can access
each of the item JSONs.
What we're gonna do is,
as you know already,
we're gonna replicate what
we have in our item list
get endpoint.
Item.json
for item in
self.items
and that's it.
Now, there's an important thing here
that often goes overlooked and that is
that there is a relationship
that has been created
as soon as we create a store model.
So, if we have many stores
and we have many items
whenever we create a store model,
we're going to go and create
an object for each item
in a database that matches that store id.
Now, if we have very
few items, that's fine
but if we have a lot of
items that can be a really
expensive operation.
So, what we can do is
we can tell SQLAlchemy
to not do that,
do not go into the items table
and create an object for each item yet.
The way we do that is we say
lazy is dynamic
and now whenever we access the JSON method
we're gonna get an error
unless
we use
.all.
So what's the key take, here?
When we use lazy equals dynamic,
self.items no longer is a list of items,
now it is a query builder
that has the ability
to look into the items table,
then we can use .all to
retrieve all of the items
in that table.
Which means that until
we call the JSON method
we are not looking into the table,
which means that creating
stores is very simple.
However, it also means that every time
we call the JSON method
we have to go into the table,
so then it is gonna be slower
and what I mean with that is
we create a store so we
load up all the items
and then we can call the
JSON method many times
for free, essentially.
If we use lazy dynamic, every
time we call the JSON method
we have to go into the table,
so then that is slower.
So, there's a trade-off there
between speed of creation
of the store and speed of
calling the JSON method
that you have to think about
which one is more important.
In our case, because the
store model gets created
when we wanna access the
data, it's gonna be like that
in our resource, I'm gonna stick with
this way of doing things but,
just food for thought, there,
something you have to
take into consideration.
Of course, something else we have to do
is go to the item model and
make sure that we're accepting
a store id there as well
and saving that to the database.
What that'll do is that'll
make sure that the store id
for the specific item model we're creating
gets assigned the value that we pass in
and that that gets put in the database.
Now that we're here, let's
go into the resources
and just make sure that
we're accepting this as well
and we don't forget later.
I'm gonna copy the add argument
and paste it in, there.
Rename it to store id,
change the type to int
and change the help message to something
a bit more helpful, like
every item needs a store id.
Now, something else to remember
is that whenever we create an item model
we're gonna have to pass in the store id.
So, for example, here in the post,
we are creating a new item,
the data that is parsed
from the parse args method
is now going to contain a store
id that we need to pass in
and similarly, down here in the put method
we have to make sure to include
data
store id.
I'll leave it up to you
to change the store id
in here, if you want as
well, which you can do.
Okay?
Also remember that data
price and data store id
can be simplified to
data
that is just going to
exactly the same thing.
It's going to pass in price as data price
and store id as data store id,
so that we can do that,
if you find that easier.
Okay?
So, that's everything for this video.
Now we've created the store model
and we've linked it up with the item.
In the next video we're going
to create the store resource,
so, I'll see you there.